<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://yoyomanzoor.github.io/Yoyomanzoor/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://yoyomanzoor.github.io/Yoyomanzoor/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-02-09T20:57:56+00:00</updated><id>https://yoyomanzoor.github.io/Yoyomanzoor/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A website for me to keep things together </subtitle><entry><title type="html">clamshell surgery</title><link href="https://yoyomanzoor.github.io/Yoyomanzoor/blog/2024/clamshell-surgery/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="clamshell surgery"/><published>2024-02-08T18:07:01+00:00</published><updated>2024-02-08T18:07:01+00:00</updated><id>https://yoyomanzoor.github.io/Yoyomanzoor/blog/2024/clamshell-surgery</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yoyomanzoor.github.io/Yoyomanzoor/blog/2024/clamshell-surgery/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="assessment-and-plan">assessment and plan</h2> <h3 id="neuro">neuro</h3> <h5 id="epidural-ropivacaine-and-pca">epidural (Ropivacaine) and PCA</h5> <p>In general, it is always worth considering whether a patient needs an epidural for pain control after surgery. As Val said, it either works well, or it doesn’t work at all and the patient is unnecessarily hypotensive, and you should consider using just PCA instead of epidural to begin with.</p> <p>If the patient is on epidural, you want to closely monitor blood pressures to make sure they don’t go hypotensive. Hypotension due to an epi is either because the epi is too deep or it’s working too well. If the patient is going hypotensive, consider a split. A split is where half of pain control is through epi and the other half is through PCA. If they are still hypotensive, you’ll need to pause the epi and switch to full PCA</p> <p>PCA is an IV pain med and will need to be switched to something PO before discharge (usually oxy)</p> <h5 id="nsaids">NSAIDs</h5> <p>Don’t give NSAIDs after a total gastrectomy!</p> <h3 id="cv">CV</h3> <h3 id="pulm">pulm</h3> <h3 id="gi">GI</h3> <h5 id="getting-off-tpn">getting off TPN</h5> <pre><code class="language-mermaid">graph TD;
    A--&gt;;
</code></pre> <pre><code class="language-mermaid">sequenceDiagram
    participant John
    participant Alice
    Alice-&gt;&gt;John: Hello John, how are you?
    John--&gt;&gt;Alice: Great!
</code></pre> <h3 id="gu">GU</h3> <h3 id="heme">heme</h3> <h5 id="when-to-get-prbcs">when to get pRBCs</h5> <p>The magic number for when to order blood transfusion is HgB &lt; 7 (or HgB &lt; 8 if relevant cardiac hx).</p> <h3 id="endo">endo</h3> <h3 id="id">ID</h3> <h3 id="dispo">dispo</h3>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="medicine"/><category term="school"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Clinical pearls I've excised from my surgery rotation]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">the piece of meat the guides the body</title><link href="https://yoyomanzoor.github.io/Yoyomanzoor/blog/2024/heart/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="the piece of meat the guides the body"/><published>2024-02-06T13:24:31+00:00</published><updated>2024-02-06T13:24:31+00:00</updated><id>https://yoyomanzoor.github.io/Yoyomanzoor/blog/2024/heart</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yoyomanzoor.github.io/Yoyomanzoor/blog/2024/heart/"><![CDATA[<arabic-text> <blockquote> <div style="text-align:right"> حَدَّثَنَا أَبُو نُعَيْمٍ، حَدَّثَنَا زَكَرِيَّاءُ، عَنْ عَامِرٍ، قَالَ سَمِعْتُ النُّعْمَانَ بْنَ بَشِيرٍ، يَقُولُ سَمِعْتُ رَسُولَ اللَّهِ صلى الله عليه وسلم يَقُولُ " الْحَلاَلُ بَيِّنٌ وَالْحَرَامُ بَيِّنٌ، وَبَيْنَهُمَا مُشَبَّهَاتٌ لاَ يَعْلَمُهَا كَثِيرٌ مِنَ النَّاسِ، فَمَنِ اتَّقَى الْمُشَبَّهَاتِ اسْتَبْرَأَ لِدِيِنِهِ وَعِرْضِهِ، وَمَنْ وَقَعَ فِي الشُّبُهَاتِ كَرَاعٍ يَرْعَى حَوْلَ الْحِمَى، يُوشِكُ أَنْ يُوَاقِعَهُ. أَلاَ وَإِنَّ لِكُلِّ مَلِكٍ حِمًى، أَلاَ إِنَّ حِمَى اللَّهِ فِي أَرْضِهِ مَحَارِمُهُ، أَلاَ وَإِنَّ فِي الْجَسَدِ مُضْغَةً إِذَا صَلَحَتْ صَلَحَ الْجَسَدُ كُلُّهُ، وَإِذَا فَسَدَتْ فَسَدَ الْجَسَدُ كُلُّهُ. أَلاَ وَهِيَ الْقَلْبُ ". </div> <br/> I heard Allah's Messenger (ﷺ) saying, 'Both legal and illegal things are evident but in between them there are doubtful (suspicious) things and most of the people have no knowledge about them. So whoever saves himself from these suspicious things saves his religion and his honor. And whoever indulges in these suspicious things is like a shepherd who grazes (his animals) near the Hima (private pasture) of someone else and at any moment he is liable to get in it. (O people!) Beware! Every king has a Hima and the Hima of Allah on the earth is His illegal (forbidden) things. Beware! There is a piece of flesh in the body if it becomes good (reformed) the whole body becomes good but if it gets spoilt the whole body gets spoilt and that is the heart. <br/><br/> Sahih al-Bukhari, 52 </blockquote> </arabic-text> <p>At this very moment, where is most of the blood in your body? The body holds between 9 and 11 liters of blood. The heart holds about half a liter of blood. Thus, the majority of our blood is held in the complex set of arteries and veins throughout the body. The heart simply provides a gradient, a positive pressure during ‘systole’ and a negative pressure during ‘diastole’ that keeps the blood circulating through the body. Through this constant pressure gradient, the heart is able to perform the heraculean feat of perfusing blood through the entire body, from the brain to the fingertips. On average, every minute, the entire volume of blood manages to circulate through the body.</p> <p>Clinically, you can imagine an infection that makes it into the blood is not good. An infection that takes root in the heart is called <strong>endocarditis</strong>. The clinical presentation includes peripheral lesions (e.g. Janeway lesions, Osler nodes) that present on the hands and feet, intraabdominal emboli that presents as damage to the kidneys or spleen, and neurologic manifestations such as seizures or weakness. In other words, infection of the heart effects the whole body.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/Yoyomanzoor/assets/img/janeway-480.webp 480w,/Yoyomanzoor/assets/img/janeway-800.webp 800w,/Yoyomanzoor/assets/img/janeway-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/Yoyomanzoor/assets/img/janeway.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Janeway lesions and Osler nodes on a hand </div> <p>Similarly, consider the idea that whatever enters the heart (spiritually) will perfuse the entire body. Just like the physical heart, there is a constant pressure being applied by the spiritual heart. Whatever seed is planted in it, the rest of the body and actions must follow. It’s the most powerful motivator. Take the example of a person that has planted the love of a video game in their heart. They will quickly find themselves addicted to playing the game they love, and spend as much time as they can playing that game. When they are not playing the game, they are thinking ‘how many hours until I can play again.’ They may even go further, buying things that remind them of the game like paraphernalia. You can replace ‘video game’ in this example with a person or another thing.</p> <arabic-text> <blockquote> <div style="text-align:right"> قال النَّبِيَّ صَلَّى اللَّهُ عَلَيْهِ وَسَلَّمَ: " مَنْهُومَانِ لَا يَشْبَعَانِ: مَنْهُومٌ فِي الْعِلْمِ لَا يَشْبَعُ مِنْهُ وَمَنْهُومٌ فِي الدُّنْيَا لَا يَشْبَعُ مِنْهَا «. رَوَى الْبَيْهَقِيُّ الْأَحَادِيثَ الثَّلَاثَةَ فِي» شُعَبِ الْإِيمَانِ </div> <br/> Two greedy ones never attain satisfaction: he who is greedy for knowledge can never get enough of it, and he who is greedy for worldly goods can never get enough of them <br/><br/> Mishkat al-Massabih 260 </blockquote> </arabic-text> <p>It is for this reason that the heart of a believer is consider a garden, where the seed of <em>iman</em> must be planted. If the garden is maintained and protected, the rest of the body will follow.</p> <p>Now consider that the physical heart is in a sheltered place, deep in our body. Endocarditis does not happen by the infectious source entering the heart directly, it must get there from outside the body, such as through heart surgery or infection of the bloodstream. Similarly, the spiritual heart also has access points. As Imam al-Ghazali points out, the spiritual heart is accessed by the eyes, the ears, the mouth, the stomach, and the limbs. Once the seed of <em>iman</em> is planted, it must be maintained by guarding those access points. Thus, as mentioned in the earlier <em>hadith</em>, it is of utmost importance to not even get close to things that will sway the heart and influence our <em>iman</em> to save our spiritual heart from an endocarditis. It is important to guard the eyes and ears, to watch our tongue, eat Halal, and act in a manner befitting a Muslim, since each of these things will help keep the heart pure and allow the rest of the body to follow suit.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="reflection"/><category term="tazkiyah"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Reflection on the heart and iman]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">git init this website</title><link href="https://yoyomanzoor.github.io/Yoyomanzoor/blog/2024/init/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="git init this website"/><published>2024-02-05T21:29:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-02-05T21:29:00+00:00</updated><id>https://yoyomanzoor.github.io/Yoyomanzoor/blog/2024/init</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yoyomanzoor.github.io/Yoyomanzoor/blog/2024/init/"><![CDATA[<p>It is currently 9:30 PM. I have to wake up tomorrow at like 4:30, prechart, and get to 5:45 rounds. This is a terrible idea, but yesterday I saw <a href="https://github.com/alshedivat/al-folio">this webpage template</a> and I decided to use it today. I should probably be doing UWorld or studying patients or doing something else, but instead here I am.</p> <p>To be fair, I had been planning on starting a blog of some sort and a place to keep my more formal writings for a while. I have been storing personal memos and writing drafts since starting medical school that I told myself I would eventually polish and publish. Hopefully by initializing this platform, I will be motivated to finish those pieces.</p> <p>Plus this gives me a platform to share my processes for things I have been doing, from art stuff to programming things.</p> <p>It’s a funny thing how we find motivation at the least opportune times.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="website"/><category term="programming"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A terrible decision]]></summary></entry></feed>